Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ג. yud gimmel.
We pick up on י"ב עמוד ב' yud bet amud bet
and we are moving on to the י"ב עמוד ב'. yud bet
amud bet.
Yes, י"ב עמוד ב'. yud bet amud bet. And we're dealing with
what happens when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has to be replaced
and the backup כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So we're about 10 lines
from the bottom, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Okay, so let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: אירע בו
פסול iravo bo psul ומינו אחר תחתיו. u'minu acher tachtav. So let's
say it actually happened that something happened to the first כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and they had to appoint the backup.
So what happens? And then the first one becomes fit again to
serve. Now, this is actually a תוספתא Tosefta and it's quoted in
הוריות, Horayot, and in the actual original context, if people know the
discussions in הוריות, Horayot, הוריות Horayot is not really about, it's not
about יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. הוריות Horayot is about different positions of
authority: מלך, Melech, כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and therefore this
issue is not limiting itself to the discussion of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur per se; could be for another purpose the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol became פסול pasul and they needed somebody to serve in his
place, although the urgency of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is particularly
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but the point is this is a
general ברייתא; Baraita; it's not even necessarily specifically talking about יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. But either way, it obviously is relevant because the whole
reason for the backup of יום כיפור Yom Kippur was in case
something happened to the first guy. So something happened to the first
guy and they appointed another one in his stead. I think the
reason I made a point about that is the language of ומינו
אחר תחתיו, u'minu acher tachtav, right? In our case, you already have
another guy waiting in the wings. So ומינו אחר תחתיו u'minu acher
tachtav sounds like we're not talking about יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
we had to go ahead and appoint somebody now because nobody was
waiting in the wings, but something happened to the first guy. But
either way, the scenario is relevant. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can't
serve, somebody else is serving in his place, and then what happens?
And then the first guy becomes fit to serve again.
That's left out, right?
Right, that's implicit, but that's left out. So ראשון, rishon, the first
guy, חוזר לעבודתו, chozer l'avodato, once he becomes fit to serve goes
back to his original position. שני, sheni, and the second guy who
had been serving in his stead, כל מצות כהונה גדולה עליו. kol
mitzvat kehuna gedola alav. He has all of the מצוות mitzvot of
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, which רש"י Rashi spells out means, you
know, he can't marry a
widow; if a close relative dies, he doesn't leave the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, he doesn't let his hair grow wild, he doesn't rend
his garments, he has to wear all eight בגדים, bgadim, the gold
בגדים bgadim when he does the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. What's not discussed, at least in רש"י, Rashi, I haven't
had a chance to see it discussed elsewhere, is: does he have
to bring the daily קרבן, korban, the daily מנחה, mincha, you know,
that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings, half in the morning, half
in the afternoon? It would be pretty funny to have two of
those being brought a day, like a regular competition of who the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is. It doesn't sound like that.
But anyway, the rest of his life?
Yes, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says he basically has a status of
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Maybe he doesn't function actively as a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol like the question I'm raising about the daily
מנחה, mincha, but he has the status for the rest of his
life as a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says: ראשון חוזר לעבודתו, rishon chozer l'avodato, yes, I agree the first
guy goes back to his job as the כהן גדול; שני Kohen
Gadol sheini אינו ראוי לא לכהן גדול ולא לכהן הדיוט. The second
guy doesn't serve as the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol; he never wears
eight בגדים, bgadim, and he doesn't serve as a כהן הדיוט. Kohen
Hedyot. Now, because, and we'll see in a minute the גמרא Gemara
will explain why, but he basically is like out of work for
the rest of his life. Bummer. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yose,
said רבי יוסי: Rabbi Yose: מעשה ביוסף בן אילם מציפורי, ma'aseh b'Yosef
ben Illem m'Tzippori, there's a story of יוסף בן אילם Yosef ben
Illem in
ציפורי, Tzippori, שאירע בו פסול בכהן גדול, she'iravo bo psul b'Kohen Gadol,
that he wasn't the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, something happened to the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, ומינוהו תחתיו, u'minuhu tachtav, and he was appointed
in his stead. So this יוסף בן אילם Yosef ben Illem was
appointed to be the stand-in for the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, Again,
not necessarily on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but anyway. ואמרו חכמים, v'amru
chachamim, and the sages say: ראשון חוזר לעבודתו, rishon chozer l'avodato, the
first guy goes back now that he's fit to serve again; שני
אינו ראוי לא לכהן גדול ולא לכהן הדיוט, sheni eino ra'ui lo
l'Kohen Gadol v'lo l'Kohen Hedyot. and the second person can't serve neither
as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. nor as a כהן הדיוט. Kohen
Hedyot. And now the גמרא Gemara explains why. כהן גדול משום איבה.
Kohen Gadol mishum eivah. Really, we're not debating רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
point. Once somebody was appointed a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to serve
in the stead, he retains that status even after the first guy
comes back. So he really is a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in
some way. But he can't serve because that will lead to enmity
and hatred and competition with the first guy, right? The
כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol whole point is that it's supposed to be
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol it's supposed to be the one person
represents, you know, the top of the כהונה. kehuna. So here now
there's somebody else who you're calling a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, at
the same time, so that's not going to be a very pleasant
situation.
כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot and the reason he's not a כהן הדיוט
Kohen Hedyot is מעלין בקודש ולא מורידין. maalin bakodesh velo moridin. Once
you got raised up, once he got the appointment of a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol even temporarily, he can't go back to his previous
status. Now, as the גמרא Gemara is going to say, what? חנוכה?
Hanukkah? What do you mean חנוכה? Hanukkah? It's the same principle about
going about about
how many candles you light.
There you go, wonderful. Now, the point is is that is that
that what that really means is, it's that his real status is
that of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol but we can't have to
we can't sort of let him function that way because of, you
know, just because of the type of conflict it will create. But
in terms of his actual הלכתי halachic status, it does seem to
be that of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, The גמרא's Gemara going
to spell out the implications. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi. We rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that the
second guy is stuck. And here are the implications: ומודה רבי יוסי
שאם עבר ועבד עבודתו כשירה. u-modeh Rabbi Yossi she-im avar ve-avad avodato
kesherah. If the second guy went out and did the עבודה avodah
and what's not said here but is presumably implicit,
if the second guy did the עבודה avodah in the בגדים begadim
of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol. of the שמונה בגדים, eight begadim,
it would actually בדיעבד be-di'avad be כשר. kasher. If a כהן הדיוט
Kohen Hedyot wore the gold garments and did the עבודה, avodah, it
would be פסול. pasul. Right? If not, you have to wear your
unique, your appropriate garments. So if this guy did the עבודה avodah
in the שמונה בגדים, eight begadim, it would be כשר. kasher. He
really does have that status of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, But
we're not going to let him do the עבודה. avodah. But in
reality because, you know, of the conflict it will create. But in
reality that is his status. Now, if that is in reality his
status, it raises other questions, which means, so presumably he's not allowed
to marry an אלמנה. almanah. Presumably, if he has a, you know,
if he's got a if an immediate relative dies, he doesn't do
קריעה, keriah, he doesn't let his hair grow wild. Right? That's what
the תורה Torah says, right? ובגדיו לא יפרום, u-vegadav lo yifrom, you
know, what's that? ושערו u-se'aro what's the פסוק? pasuk? Why don't you
tell me? Ah, what is it? והכהן הגדול מאחיו אשר יוצק על
ראשו שמן המשחה
ומלא את ידו ללבוש את הבגדים את ראשו לא יפרע ובגדיו לא
יפרום.
Ve-hakohen hagadol me-echav asher yutzak al rosho shemen hamishchah
u-mile et yado lilvosh et habegadim
et rosho lo yifra u-vegadav lo yifrom. I can't... anyway,
but okay. He doesn't... do you hand me the חומש Chumash there?
Thank you.
Yeah, Rabbi Elazar. Yeah, I really do think it might be... what
do you think about that? Really is the קשר kesher to חנוכה?
Hanukkah? That's a big deal.
Alright, yeah, have idea,
sure. No, but that idea is used in multiple places, you know?
So,
this is not a primary it doesn't emerge here as its primary.
No, I don't think so. I don't think so.
Hold on. Okay, anyway, so here we go as...
I'm sorry. Okay, so here's what it says about כהן הגדול מאחיו
Kohen Hagadol me-echav in אמור. Emor. אשר יוצק על ראשו שמן המשחה
ומלא את ידו ללבוש את הבגדים את ראשו לא יפרע ובגדיו לא
יפרום.
asher yutzak al rosho shemen hamishchah u-mile et yado lilvosh et habegadim
et rosho lo yifra
u-vegadav lo yifrom. Okay? ועל כל נפשות מת לא יבא לאביו ולאמו
לא יטמא. ve-al kol nafshot met lo yavo le-aviv u-le-imo lo yitamma.
So he's not allowed to become טמא tamei even to his father
and mother if his immediate relative dies. Cannot let his hair grow
long. He cannot rend his garments. So presumably that would still apply
to him, right? If he really is the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
The only thing we're actually saying is don't do the עבודה. avodah.
So that raises that question still is a little bit, you know,
when the language is he's not חוזר, chozer, presumably רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi as the גמרא Gemara only points out the implication if he
did the עבודה, avodah, but presumably he's not debating about his status
as well for other הלכות. halachot. It's just we don't actually let
him do the עבודה. avodah. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הלכה כרבי
יוסי. Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi. ומודה רבי יוסי
u-modeh Rabbi Yossi we just heard... הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi.
So another statement is that we rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
And another statement is ומודה רבי יוסי שאם מת ראשון שחוזר לעבודתו
u-modeh Rabbi Yossi she-im met rishon she-chozer la-avodato
that if the first guy died then this guy becomes the next
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. פשיטא, Pshita, isn't that obvious? I mean he's
been a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. all along we've been saying, right?
It's just we don't let him serve because of the conflict. So
מהו דתימא הוי ליה צר מחייו, mahu deteima hava leh tzar mechayim,
maybe I would be afraid that even if he weren't serving, but
if the current כהן גדול Kohen Gadol knew that as soon as
I die this guy's going to step into my place, so who
wants to go around waiting is there somebody there waiting for me
to die? Right? So that's not pleasant either. Not just if he's
serving does it create a sense of conflict. The fact that he's
in the wings and waiting to take over my position as soon
as I die, that also is like a competitor while I'm alive.
That also isn't pleasant. So maybe we wouldn't allow that to happen.
Maybe this guy would not get a chance to step in even
after the first guy died. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that
we're not concerned about that. Okay? So that obviously is relevant for
us because our whole discussion is about the substitute
for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, what
happens if it actually ends... And the basic, it seems that everybody,
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei both agree that the
first, that the substitute obtains the personal status of a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol The question is, is he now allowed to actually go
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and serve as such? Not on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but during the rest of the year, can
he wear the eight garments and serve as such? So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says yes and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says no, that
will create too much conflict, we don't let that happen. But what
we will let happen is once the first guy dies, he will
take his place. And בדיעבד bedi'eved if he did put on the
eight garments and serve, that would be כשר. kosher. And also Zev
pointed out presumably therefore בדיעבד bedi'eved
all the restrictions of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol. all the הלכות
halachot of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, particularly when relatives die, would
apply to him. The only debate boils down to are we going
to actually let him serve or not because of the conflict that
that will create. Okay, so now we get to the, that was
the, as it touches on the משנה, Mishnah, now we actually get
back to the משנה, Mishnah, which is the question about do we
create a substitute wife, not only a substitute כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
a backup כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, So רבי יהודה אומר אף אשה
אחרת מתקינין לו. Rabbi Yehuda omer af isha acheret matkinin lo. They
would even create for him a backup wife. Because it says וכיפר
בעדו ובעד ביתו, vechiper ba'ado uve'ad beito, his household means he has
to be married. And the חכמים Chachamim say back, אם כן אין
לדבר סוף, im ken ein ladavar sof, if you have to worry
that his wife will die, so you have to worry that the
backup wife will die and there's no end to it. So the
גמרא Gemara says רבנן נמי הכא חיישי לשמא. Rabbanan nami hacha chayishi
leshema. So why are the רבנן Rabbanan not concerned? Why are the
רבנן Rabbanan only concerned that maybe he'll become טמא? tamei? Why aren't
they concerned that maybe his wife will die? Once we're concerned, isn't
that a reasonable concern as well? So אמרו לך רבנן, amru lecha
Rabbanan, the רבנן Rabbanan will say back to you, טומאה שכיחא. tumah
shchicha. No, becoming טמא tamei is something that's more common. You know,
it's not so unlikely to become טמא tamei especially if it includes
seminal emission and other people who are טמא tamei touching you. It's
something that occurs on a pretty regular basis. מיתה לא שכיחא, mitah
lo shchicha, death is not so common. So therefore that one particular
person will die דווקא davka on today, that's a very tiny concern,
that we're not going to be concerned about. Okay, so that's why
they're not, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is concerned about it. So
אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
אם כן אין לדבר סוף, im ken ein ladavar sof, if you're
going to worry about his wife dying you should worry about the
backup wife dying.
And the גמרא Gemara says שפיר קאמרי ליה לרבי יהודה, shapir ka'amrei
lei le-Rabbi Yehuda, that was a good retort. So רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say back to them, אמר לך
למיטה דחד חיישינן, amar lecha lemitah dechad chayshinan, for one person dying,
that's the level of concern I have, that's already not a crazy
concern. ומיטה דתרתי לא חיישינן, u-mitah detartei lo chayshinan, that two people
should die, both the wife and the backup wife, well חיישינן chayshinan
that's already a crazy scenario, that I'm not going to be concerned
about. רבנן, Rabbanan, and the רבנן Rabbanan would say back to him,
איכא למיחש אפילו
למיטה דתרתי חיישינן,
hika lemichash
afilu lemitah detartei chayshinan, if you want to start being concerned about
those scenarios, אפילו למיטה דתרתי חיישינן, afilu lemitah detartei chayshinan, you should
be concerned that two people will die. Presumably what they're saying is
look, we are concerned about reasonable concerns that he'll become טמא, tamei,
what's the likelihood? About five percent. That's a reasonable concern. Your concern
his wife will die today, that's what, one in a thousand, one
in a hundred thousand? Once you're concerned about crazy possibilities, okay, if
you're concerned in a one in a hundred thousand chance, then you
can be concerned in a one in a million chance. What's the
difference? You're already concerning yourself about crazy possibilities. So once you're no
longer being reasonable about your concerns, there's no reason to stop at
one. Okay, that's a pretty good response. Okay, once איכא למיחש, hika
lemichash, once you're being concerned about those scenarios, אפילו למיטה דתרתי חיישינן,
afilu lemitah detartei chayshinan, you should be concerned that two people will
die.
רבנן, Rabbanan, now the גמרא Gemara says the רבנן, Rabbanan, נימא אינהו
לנפשייהו, nima inhu lenafshaihu, why don't they say that to themselves? If
we're concerned you'll be טמא, tamei, let's be concerned that both him
and the backup guy will become טמא. tamei. Now again, there seems
to be a pretty reasonable answer, not what the answer the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, but the answer is the רבנן Rabbanan
are saying we are concerned like they're very
much statisticians or actuaries and they're saying you know we're concerned about
you know up to five percent likelihood we're concerned. So that doesn't
include death, it includes טומאה, tumah, but it doesn't include two people
because טומאה שכיחא, tumah shchicha, that's what they're saying. טומאה שכיחא, tumah
shchicha, anything other than טומאה, tumah, one person dying, two people becoming
טמא, tamei, that's לא שכיחא, lo shchicha, be concerned squared.
That's fine but שכיחא, shchicha,
the fact that people become טמא tamei is שכיחא, shchicha, the fact
that this particular person becomes טמא tamei maybe is still שכיחא, shchicha,
what is it, one in twenty? The fact that two specific people
become טמא tamei is one in four hundred. Do the math. So
the fact that as a category it's שכיחא shchicha might be true
but the fact that this particular scenario will happen is a לא
שכיחא.
lo shchicha. I'm just saying it's qualitatively different argument because
The answer is that for two specific people to have it happen
to is already below the threshold. Their whole challenge for רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is he had no reasonable threshold, so he'd be concerned
about everything. But they have a reasonable threshold. But the גמרא Gemara
says, look, let's challenge you yourself. If you're going to be concerned
about one person for טומאה, tumah, be concerned about two people. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי לך רבנן, amri lecha Rabbanan, the Rabbis
will say back to you, כהן גדול זריז הוא. Kohen Gadol zariz
hu. No, no, no, you don't have to worry about that. The
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. is careful. So therefore it's not going to
happen. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי זריז הוא, ee zariz hu,
if he's so careful, למה מתקינין כהן אחר? lama matkinin Kohen acher?
Why do you have a backup? כיון דעבדינן ליה
צרה, keivan de-avdinan leh tzarah, ah that's exactly it, sort of echoing
the discussion before about the
competitor. Once we've got a competitor waiting in the wings, so כל
שכן דזריז טפי. kol sheken de-zariz tfei. That'll make him more careful.
So basically what they're saying is, and as רש״י Rashi points out,
טומאה tumah is preventable. You know, there are some things, of course,
some things you can never prevent. But by and large, טומאה tumah
is preventable. So therefore the carefuler you are and the more, sort
of motivated you are, then the less likely it'll happen. Whereas death
is not preventable. So therefore it doesn't,
nothing is going to say, oh now you'll be super careful and
make sure that you don't die, right? That's obviously not relevant. So
the גמרא's Gemara answer is that by having a backup we're not
really concerned about what will happen, because then we should be concerned
about both people will become טמא. tamei. But what we do is
by having a backup it forces him to be much more on
his toes and that'll actually, that's really addressing our concerns. Our concerns
are really getting him to be as super careful as possible, not
the theoretical likelihood that something will happen. It's what are we going
to do to get him to be super careful. And therefore we
have a backup. But רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, let's be concerned about
the theoretical likelihood that something will happen. Somebody will drop dead. No
matter what you do, that possibility is going to be the same.
So once you're concerned about that and once that is pretty
far-fetched, what's to stop you at one person? You should even have
a backup of a backup. Okay, so that's what the Rabbis say.
Again, the whole thing could have just been answered based on statistics,
that they're saying we're limiting ourselves to common, two people isn't common,
your uncommon, what's the difference? Either way, that's their challenge to him,
that there's no, why just stop at one? Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ומי
סגי ליה בתקנתא סבתא, umi sagi leh betakanta speta, בתקנתא? betakanta? Since
when is the backup going to work? Okay, so now we're asking
within רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. We get that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
wants to have a backup wife. How will that backup work? ביתו
אמר רחמנא והכא לאו ביתו הוא. beiso amar Rachmana vehacha lav beiso
hu. So it says your household, your wife. So even if you
have another woman waiting in the wings, you're there in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So his wife dies, so there's another woman. Big
deal! He's not married to her. What have you accomplished? So the
גמרא Gemara says, דמקדש
לה.
demkadesh
lah. Okay fine, so he marries her before יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So she's also his wife. He has two wives. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והא כמה דלא כניס לה לאו ביתו הוא. vehachama de-lo
kanis lah lav beiso hu. One minute, בית bayis generally means not
just married, but it actually means not just
קידושין, kiddushin, betrothal,
but it means נישואין. nisuin.
Actual, actual
like for us it means חופה, chuppah, but they basically start living
together as husband and wife. So the תורה Torah describes as מי
האיש אשר ארש אשה ולא לקחה, mi ha-ish asher eiras isha velo
lekacha, right? So the idea of לוקח, lokeiach, although לוקח lokeiach is
used
rabbinically to mean the act of קידושין, kiddushin, like the giving of
an object of value, כסף kesef and so on, in the תורה
Torah it's very often associated with the act of sex, like כי
יקח איש אשה ובא אליה, ki yikach ish isha uba eileha, right?
So the idea that אשר ארש אשה ולא לקחה asher eiras isha
velo lekacha means that the act of קידושין kiddushin was done. Technically
she's his wife, but they have not yet begun to actually physically
live together as husband and wife, which is called נישואין. nisuin. Or
לכנס likaneis here means to bring her in, bring her into his
household and that's the second stage of נישואין. nisuin. And the גמרא
Gemara generally assumes
that the word בית bayis refers to living together as husband and
wife, refers to that second stage of נישואין. nisuin. So the גמרא
Gemara says, I don't get it. So first, so what there's another
woman, not his wife? Okay he does קידושין kiddushin before יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Okay but קידושין kiddushin isn't enough, they have to actually
start living together. So the גמרא Gemara says they have to be
נישואין. nisuin. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הלאו ביתו? halav beiso? דכניסה dekanisa fine, he did נישואין, nisuin, he
brought her into his house, they did start living together before יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. אם כן הוו ליה שני בתים. im kein havu
leh shnei batim. So now he has two households, two wives. ורחמנא
אמר וכפר בעדו ובעד ביתו, verachmana amar vechiper ba-ado uva-ad beiso, his
house, ולא בעד שני בתים, velo ba-ad shnei batim, not two houses,
which is quite fascinating, right? Because here you are in a polygamous
society which allows for a man to be married to two wives,
and the גמרא Gemara actually tells us that a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol can't be married to two wives, at least on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. He can only be married to one wife. You know,
it's an interesting idea, right, when we talk about... It's the whole
echoing here of concepts of competing wives, right, and competing כהנים, Kohanim,
right, the whole סוגיא sugya in יבמות Yevamot that talks about, you
know, if there are two co-wives, they're considered צרות, tzarot, like competitors
with one another. Right, right. Well, no, it's from ואשה אל אחותה
לא תקח לצרור לגלות ערותה עליה. v'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror
legalot ervatah aleiha. So the two wives are competing wives, the whole
concept of a צרה. tzara. So the גמרא Gemara right before said,
the other כהן גדול Kohen Gadol waiting in the wings, or the
other כהן גדול Kohen Gadol after one has been replaced and then
took back, is called the צרה, tzara, like the competitor. The whole
idea is that there's an understanding that of a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol there should only be one, right, only one כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol, He's like the head. You don't have two כהנים גדולים. Kohanim
Gedolim. So here, too, it's quite interest and the whole idea thinking
about, you know, this idea of two and competitors. So here you
have a similar an interesting point, that the that the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol. is only supposed to have one wife. At least, again,
at least on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the idea of בעדו ובעד
ביתו, ba'ado uva'ad beito, right? So, so we I don't see that
anywhere else, this idea of a focus on it. There's issues about
how much, you know, did the גמרא Gemara endorse and like the
idea of two wives or not like the idea. There's actually a
difference. The בבלי Bavli seems much more okay with it than the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi and so on. But this real idea that הלכתית, halachically,
there's a point of just having one wife and not two wives,
once הלכה halacha allows for it, you're really just finding here, again,
not all the time by כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol but at least
by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, which is interesting thinking about the earlier
discussion, which focuses on also the unique, the singular role of the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, here also the, you know, only one singular
wife. So the גמרא Gemara says, that's not possible now, to have
two wives.
דבעדו ובעד ביתו ולא בשני בתים, de-ba'ado uva'ad beito v'lo bishnei batim,
not two
households. So דהדר מגרש לה. dehador migaresh lah.
Fine, he divorces her. He marries her, he does נישואין, nisu'in, he
divorces her. Of course, if he divorces her, you're back to square
one. So אי מגרש לה הדר קושיא לדוכתא, ei migaresh lah hadar
kushya l'duchta, so we're back to square one. You only what happens
is his first wife dies. לא, צריכה דmגרש לה על תנאי. lo,
tzericha demigaresh lah al tnai. Now what the גמרא's Gemara going to
do is going to get into a whole discussion about how to
arrange it so you have a גט get that's on condition that
only kicks in at the moment you need it to kick in,
so that you'll only be married to one wife at any one
time, but you'll always be married to one wife. So if one
wife dies, you'll be married to the other. She doesn't die, you'll
only be married to the first. And the גמרא's Gemara going to
go and try to figure all of this out, okay? It gets
a little bit not so much I would say complicated as much
as like the suggestions are almost silly suggestions that initially, they're like
obvious why they're wrong. And רש״י Rashi actually says this. If you
just take a minute, I'll just before we start reading it in
the גמרא, Gemara, I'll read you the רש״י. Rashi. If you look
at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says like this, I'm going to tell
you,
it's like four lines down in the narrow lines, רש״י Rashi says,
וכל סוג סוגיא זו אין תירוצים שבה יכולים לעמוד כי יש להם
תשובות רבות. ve-chol sug sugya zo ein teirutzim she-ba yecholim la'amod ki
yesh lahem teshuvot rabbot. So he says every single suggestion the גמרא's
Gemara going to make is like there's a million questions on it.
ואינו אלא כמלמדין אותנו ואם תאמר כן יש להשיב כן ואינו משיב
כל תשובות שיש להשיב. ve-eino ella kemelamdin otanu v'im tomar ken yesh
lehashiv ken ve-eino meshiv kol teshuvot she-yesh lehashiv. It's not going to
there's a million things you could say to respond to every single
line the גמרא's Gemara about to say. כי באחת הוא מסלקו לתרץ
עניין אחר עד שהעמידה על מכונה. ki be'achat hu mesalko leteretz inyan
acher ad she-he'emidah al mechona. So there's going to be a lot
of bad suggestions till we get to the right explanation. Okay, so
as we're reading this through, you're going to say, "But that's crazy,
of course that won't work." So רש״י Rashi already preempts you. Yeah,
I know, all these a lot of these suggestions are crazy. We're
going to try to we're working it through, like thinking out loud,
to figure out how we can get it so he can actually
be married to to always one woman, but only one woman at
a time. Now you realize, the whole problem is created because of
the concept of נישואין. nisu'in. Because if it was only an idea
of קידושין, kidushin, it would be very easy. You would take one
woman aside who wasn't his wife and say, "Here is the ring.
You are מקודשת mekudeshet to me on the condition that my wife
dies sometime today." And the קידושין kidushin will take place the minute
that she dies. And that would be perfect. If the wife if
his wife never died, the קידושין kidushin wouldn't take effect. If the
wife died at 3:02 PM, then the then the קידושין kidushin would
take effect at 3:02 PM and he transitioned from being married to
wife one to being married to wife two. It would be very
simple. You just marry the second one on the condition and it
and then it takes effect at the time that the first one
dies. But because the גמרא Gemara introduced the idea of נישואין, nisu'in,
we've got a problem. Because נישואין nisu'in is a is a reality.
It can't be done on a condition. You can't say, "Here I
am, I'm taking you into your house, we're living together as husband
and wife on the condition that..." Okay?
It's just it's effected by the reality of them living together. So
you can't make the status of נישואין nisu'in kick in automatically at
the minute you need it to kick in.
You have to say as if.
You can't. You have to do it you have to create the
reality of the נישואין, nisu'in, because that can only be done by
the lived reality, it cannot be done on the condition that and
to take effect at a later time. So you have to actually
create the lived
reality. And now you have to work at eliminating one of them
at you know and that there should only be one and how
do you manage to eliminate? And then it becomes very complicated with
this whole discussion of גט, get, but it would be a lot
easier if it could just be done based without the נישואין, nisuein,
done based with קידושין kiddushin and done בתינאי. bitnai. Yes, Rivka.
Is this second woman
only in waiting? She something is going to happen to her whether
it's נישואין nisuein or קידושין, kiddushin, she can no longer she's not
going to be able to marry another כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, right?
I'm just at מעלין בקודש maalin bakodesh thing.
No, that's
not going to happen to her. She's right.
Well, she might be a גרושה, gerusha, yes. No, the idea of
מעלין בקודש maalin bakodesh doesn't apply to people that were married to
a כהן. kohen. A woman married to a כהן kohen yes, can't
marry a כהן. kohen.
She can never marry a כהן. kohen. Right.
She can marry a ישראל. Yisrael.
What does she get out of it? Not much. It is very
degrading. I know, a woman in this position and to even
discuss it, right, this woman she's not spoken about as though she
is a real person.
Right.
Degrading for the first wife also, right? It's degrading for the first
wife we're like planning her potential death.
Yeah, I mean this
one she says maybe, maybe she'll marry. Right. You're right. It's you're
right. It's completely she's completely being used to function as this ביתו,
beito, right, to satisfy this הלכה halakhic requirement.
Whether it's theoretical, not theoretical, it remains as an index that women
are there to be
used, מופך פה מופך שם, mupach po mupach sham, doesn't matter, her
life doesn't matter. She's got to fulfill this function that has nothing
to do with her.
Right. Okay, I
okay, I can't say anything, I mean you're right. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says all right, so let's see now how we're
going to try to figure this out. So he has them both
נישואין. nisuein. And now we've got to get it so that he's
only married to one of them at the right time. So דהדר
מגרש לה, dehadeir megarish lah, he would divorce her. אי מגרש לה
הדר קשיא לדוכתי. ei megarish lah hadeir kushya leduchtei. לא צריכא דמגרש
לה על תנאי. lo tzricha demegarish lah al tnai. He would divorce
the second one on a condition. What's the condition? דאמר לה deamar
lah he says to her הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתמותי. harei
zeh gitteich al menat shetamuti. Here's your גט get on the condition
that you die. Now that's of course like we said crazy. I
mean if she dies then okay
then you know then she doesn't so much need the גט get
and he's anyway only married to the first one. So the גמרא
Gemara says ודילמא לא מתה, v'dilma lo meita, maybe she doesn't die
and we're back to square one והוו לה שתי בתי. v'havu lah
shtei batei. He's married to two
wives, right? That doesn't work to say your גט get if you
die. אלא דאמר לה הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תמותי. ela
deamar lah harei zeh gitteich al menat shelo tamuti.
Here's your גט get if you don't die. Okay, so if she
doesn't die and they both live then it's her גט get and
he's only married to wife one.
You're talking about she doesn't die on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. יום
כיפור.
Yom Kippur. So the גמרא Gemara says אי לא מתה ei lo
meita
if she doesn't die מגרש לה megarish lah then he'd be divorced
from her and be only married to wife one. That'd work.
Okay. ואי מתה v'ei meita if she does
die,
הכא קיימא haka kaima then she's
married... sorry,
if she does
die then הכא קיימא haka kaima then let's see it
again. אי לא מתה ei lo meita if she doesn't die wife
number two then מגרש לה megarish lah then she's
divorced, she's out of the picture and he's married to wife number
one. ואי מתה v'ei meita if she does die then she's not
divorced okay and
הכא קיימא haka kaima he's still married and he's still married to
wife number one. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute ודילמא אי
לא מתה
והוה לה
גיטא דהאי גיטא ומית...
v'dilma ei lo meita v'hava lah gita
dehai gita umit... I gotta write this out.
Hold on. There you go. I'm sorry. Here's wife number one.
Okay. There's wife number one and there's wife number two. Okay. Okay
so now what's the condition? The condition is על מנת שלא
תמותי.
al menat shelo tamuti.
So this is your גט get if you don't die. Okay?
So if she lives it's going to be then she's going to
be divorced. It'll be a גט. get.
At what point?
Well we'll discuss at what point in a minute. Okay? So then
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי לא מתה מגרש לה.
ei lo meita megarish lah. So if she doesn't die then she's
divorced. So scenario number one is so what are the scenarios? The
scenarios
are wife number let's take the scenarios.
Here's wife number one. Yep. Let's do it like this. Right? There
are four scenarios basically.
This is wife
number
No, there're four possible scenarios of what's going to happen on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, right?
Okay, so let's take a look. It says like this, so אילו
לא מתה, Ilu lo mesa, so she lived, okay? So she's going
to live. If she lives, what's going to happen? She'll be divorced.
Okay, so if she's divorced and you can just do this, if
she's divorced, so she's out of the picture. So then he has
one wife here. Of course, if she dies, if she dies and
she lives, you've got a problem. You see that, right? Because if
wife number one dies,
wife number one dies and wife number two lives, right, she's divorced
and then he has no wives. Alright, but anyway it says if
she, so anyway if she lives she's divorced and you've got this.
Don't you have to chart it out with the wives and the
vertical column lives, dies, lives, dies and then divorced, not divorced? No,
because the divorce results from this. Okay, let's take a look. If
she lives, if she lives then she becomes
divorced, right? And then if she lives, you're okay because then you
have one wife. So that's good.
Okay? So then you've got one wife and you're good. Okay? So
אילו לא מתה נתגרשה לה, Ilu lo mesa nitgarsha lah, that's good.
Can she marry somebody at the time of marriage?
Yes, קידושין Kiddushin yes, נישואין Nissuin no. So that's why it has
to be conditional divorce.
You can't marry somebody else saying at the time of marriage I'm
gonna divorce her in a week
if she
lives, if she lives.
Okay, let's finish this. Okay. אילו לא מתה, Ilu lo mesa, if
she lives, נתגרשה לה nitgarsha lah she'll be divorced. So she'll be
divorced and then you'll have one, and then she'll live and then
you'll have one wife. That'll be good. Okay.
ואם מתה, Ve'im mesa, if she dies, so if she dies then
she's dead so she doesn't need to be divorced, so she's out
of the picture, and you'll also, and number one will live so
you'll also have one wife, so you're good. אילו לא מתה נתגרשה
לה ואם מתה קיימא הכא. Ilu lo mesa nitgarsha lah ve'im mesa
kayma hacha. So in either way, either whether she lives or dies,
you'll still have the first wife. Of course, the whole point of
the backup was if number one would die, so it doesn't really
work. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואם מתה קיימא הכא. ve'im mesa
kayma hacha. גמרא Gemara says one minute, ודילמא אי לא מתה והוי
לה גיטא דהאי גיטא מתה חברתה. vedilma i lo mesa vehavei lah
gita dehai gita mesa chaverta. Maybe she doesn't die and then she's
divorced with this גט, get, and the first one dies, which is
what the whole point was. וקם לה בלא בית, Vekam lah belo
bayis, this is crazy, because either way, either she'll be divorced or
die, either way she's out of the picture. So you haven't covered
any of the cases where the first woman dies, which is exactly
what this whole thing was supposed to be.
Okay, wait, so is she gonna be divorced right at the end?
Well, we'll get there. אלא דאמר לה. Ela de'amar lah. Okay, let's
try again. אלא דאמר לה על מנת שתמות אחת מכם. Ela de'amar
lah al menas shetamus achas michem. If one of you dies, that's
the condition. Okay,
so מתה הא קיימא הכא מתה
הך קיימא הכא.
mesa ha
kayma hacha mesa hach kayma hacha.
So if one of you dies, okay? If one of you dies,
you're divorced. So if you die, okay, and then check, then she
lives, that's one wife.
Okay, because you're divorced, you're out of the picture. If she dies,
okay, then
the other one lives. She's the other one lives, but if just
one of you dies, that's crazy, because if one of you dies
then she's divorced and then you've got zero.
So actually it doesn't work.
Okay, so let's take a look.
אלא, Ela, where were we? דאמר לה על מנת
שתמות אחת מכם. De'amar lah al menas shetamus achas michem. If one
of you dies. מתה הא קיימא הכא מתה הך קיימא הכא. Mesa
ha kayma hacha mesa hach kayma hacha. גמרא Gemara says one minute,
ודילמא לא מתה ולא חד מנייהו. vedilma lo mesa velo chad minayhu.
Maybe nobody dies. והוו לה שני בתים. Vhavei lah shnei batim.
Number one, if they both live, you're stuck because it's only a
גט get if one of them dies. Number two, and anyway, even
in this scenario also you have no wife because it's a גט.
get. So גמרא Gemara says, ועוד כי האי גוונא מי הוה גיטא.
ve'od ki hai gavna mi havei gita.
And anyway that wouldn't be a גט. get. ואמר רבא, Va'amar Rava,
רבא Rava says, הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תשתי יין כל
ימי חיי. Harei zeh giteich al menas shelo tishsi yayin kol yemei
chayai.
If a man says to a woman, here is your גט get
on the condition that you don't drink wine as long as I
am alive, חיי, chayai, or you're alive, אין זה כריתות. ein zeh
kerisus. It's not a good divorce because it's a condition that she's
bound to for her entire life, or for the man's entire life,
which means that they're still connected to each other as long as
they both live, whereas the whole idea of a divorce is that
it separates them during their lives. כל ימי חיי פלוני, Kol yemei
chayei ploni, as long as you don't drink wine while a certain
person is alive, הרי זה כריתות. harei zeh kerisus. That's good. So
you can't say this is your גט get on the condition that,
that you die, or you know, because then it means that
the גט get is. Yes, it's
a conditional
גט get they're saying. What? Yes, that's the whole סוגיא sugya in
גיטין. Gittin. Yes, and I know the obvious problems with עגונה, aguna,
yes. Okay, those weren't the scenarios the גמרא Gemara is talking about,
but it's basically...
How would they enforce that, you know, at the time of marriage?
That is, there is, some people had suggested that. Okay. That, yeah.
So the גמרא Gemara says two things. First of all, on the
condition that one of you dies, which I don't even know why
the גמרא Gemara even takes the possibility, because obviously in this case
neither shall be married to neither of them. But the other point
the גמרא Gemara says is, if it's on the condition that you
die, then
then she's bound by that condition her entire life, and that's not
a good condition anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אלא דאמר
לה, ella de'amar lah, let's try again. הרי זה גיטך על מנת
שלא תמות חברתך. Harei zeh gitteich al menas shelo tamus chaverteich. So
on the condition that the other woman doesn't die. Now that can
be. As long as it's not conditional on your life, it's a
good condition. On the condition that wife number one doesn't die. So
let's see how that plays out. אילו מיתה חברתך מגורשה. Ilo misa
chaverteich megarsha. If so, if if number one lives, now we're getting
closer, right? This is your גט get on the condition that essentially
number one is alive on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Now that's a
lot closer to what we want to say. So if wife number
one lives through יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, she's divorced. Good, only have
wife number one. ואם מיתה, Ve'im misa, if number one dies on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so then it's not a good גט. get.
והקיימא הא, Vehakaima ha, and now you've got number two. So that's
perfect, right? Basically, you say it that that should be very simple.
You know, this at least what we'll see the problem, but at
least this is getting us on the right track. This is your
גט get on the condition that she lives through lives through יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. So if she lives through יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you're out of the picture. If she doesn't live through יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, it's not your גט, get, and he's married to wife
number two. Very nice. But now we get to Rivka's question, which
is when did she die?
Which is the last line, the very the very beginning of the
last line. How do you read it with the three has?
אילו מיתה
והקיימא.
Ilo misa
ha kaima.
What do you do with that?
Wait wait wait. Okay. אילו מיתה חברתך מגורשה. Ilo misa chaverteich megarsha.
ואם מיתה הא, Ve'im misa ha, and if this one dies, והקיימא
הא. Vehakaima ha. The middle הא ha is is הרי. harei. הרי
קיימא זה, harei kaima zeh, מתקיים. miskayem. Right. אם מיתה זו הרי
קיימא זו. Im misa zo harei kaima zo. Right. Okay. ודילמא, Vedilma,
so now so now we're good. גמרא Gemara says wait a minute.
ודילמא
מיתה חברתך בפלגא דעבודה. Vedilma misa chaverteich bepaga de'avoda. Here's the problem.
Wife number one dies at noon. Okay. So you basically said if
she if if the first wife dies, it's not a גט. get.
So if if the first wife dies, it's not a גט, get,
because then he'll be married to the second. Lovely. But if the
first wife dies at noon, then it's not a גט get and
for the first half of the day he was married to two
wives. ואיגלאי מילתא למפרע, Ve'igla milsa lemafrei'a, and it turns out retroactively,
דגיטא דהאי לאו גיטא הוא, degitta dehai lav gitta hu, because the
first wife died, it wasn't a גט get because now he needed
to be married to the second one. ועבד ליה עבודה בשני בתים,
Va'avad lei avoda bishnei batim, and then the first half of the
day he had two wives. Right? Is that clear? Yes? People lost
somewhat? Okay.
He had two wives going
into the day, then he was going to remain married to number
two. Wait a second.
But wait a second. But מיתה בפלגא דעבודה, misa bepaga de'avoda, right?
If she dies if she dies,
then she stays his wife. Not she becomes his wife, she stays
his wife. Right. So if she lives, then two is out of
the picture. If one dies, then two not just doesn't become his
wife, stays his wife. Right. So here's the question: but if one
died in the middle of the day, then two stayed his wife,
but the first half of the day they were overlapping.
But how could he have gone into being כהן גדול Kohen Gadol,
when he was married to two wives?
Because if it would work out that she would have died at
the beginning of the day, or she wouldn't have died at all,
then there would only have been one wife. Right, but at... That's
base... that's basically
what the גמרא Gemara is asking. He was alive. That's what the
גמרא Gemara is asking.
In the scenario where not that she lives,
and not that she dies at the beginning of the day, but
that she dies in the middle of the day, there's always going
to be an overlap for the beginning of the day. That's exactly
what it's asking.
Wait, so I just want to make absolutely certain I understand. So
in other words, on יום כיפור Yom Kippur came and he was
married to two wives. So he can't do the עבודה avoda as
of that moment.
No, he can, because if one if if the first one lives,
retroactively he'll never have been married he'll be divorced from the second
and he'll only have been married to one. If the first one
died before he began the עבודה, avoda, he'll only have been married
to the second. What you're saying is yeah, but if the first
one dies in the middle of the day, he'll have been overlap.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is asking.
No, but what I'm saying is if she doesn't die until the
middle of the day, why doesn't the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol שני
already kick in as the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol?
We can't retroactively make him kick in.
You're saying if she hasn't died at the beginning of the day,
maybe she'll live out the day. Yeah.
It's only going to be a problem if she dies in the
middle of the day. Okay. Possibility. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara asks
like this. אלא דאמר לה. Ella de'amar lah. All right. הרי זה
גיטך על מנת שתמות חברתך. Harei zeh gittech al menat shetamut chavertech.
It's, here is your גט get if my first wife dies. So
one minute, how's that going to solve it? Because obviously if the
first wife lives, he has two wives, right? If it's a גט
get if my first wife dies. And this is ודילמא מיתה חברתה.
vedilma meitah chaverta.
Maybe,
so first I mean you could have said I would have said
maybe they both live and it's not a גט. get. But he's
saying, the גמרא Gemara is saying, ודילמא מיתה חברתה. vedilma meitah chaverta.
Let's say the first wife dies והוה ליה גיטא, vehava leh gitta,
it will be a גט. get. דהאי גיטא, Dehai gitta, דהאי גיטא,
dehai gitta, וקאי בלא בית, vekai belo bayit, and he'll have no
wives. I mean that was a crazy answer. We were very close.
You don't solve the problem by just suggesting the opposite.
Right? By saying it's your גט, get, it's your גט get if
my first wife doesn't die was close. We had the overlap problem.
By saying it's your גט get if my first wife does die
does not make it any better. Okay, it makes it worse. It
means I could be a, I could have two wives or no
wives. It's not going to solve the problem. אלא דמגרש להו לתרוייהו.
Ella demagaresh lehu letarvaihu.
Ah, here's what we're going to do. We're going to divorce both
wives, Rivka, you were upset that the first, the second one was
being objectified, now they both get objectified. Okay, he divorces both wives.
ולחדא אמר לה הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תמות חברתך. Ulechada
amar lah harei zeh gittech al menat shelo tamut chavertech. To number
one he said, it's your גט get if two doesn't die. ולחדא
אמר לה הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תיכנסי לבית הכנסת. Ulechada
amar lah harei zeh gittech al menat shelo tikanesi leveit haknesset. Now
how does that work? So number two he says this will be
your גט, get, this will be your גט get if one, if
one lives, if number one lives. Okay, so that makes sense. Number
one lives out the whole day and then two is out of
the picture. That solves that problem.
Okay. Question is, let's say that, fine, if number one, if number
one dies in the middle of the day though we've got a
problem, right? Because if number one dies in the middle of the
day then she remains the wife and there's the overlap. So what
we have to do in that scenario, if number one dies in
the middle of the day, is in the case that number one
dies in the middle of the day we've got to get number
one to be divorced. Right? Is that true? Because if number one
dies in the middle of the day
she's going to be, she'll be the wife for the whole day.
So what we have to do is figure out how to get
one out of the picture for the first half of the day
if she dies at noon. So the way you get her out
of the picture is you give her a גט get and you
say now, what we really should say is here's your גט get
which will take effect if you die during the day. That would
have solved it, right? The real way to solve it is this
is your
גט get now and ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur if you
die sometime in the middle of the
day. So then if she dies in the middle of the day
she's divorced and she remains the wife. If she lives throughout the
day then she's out of the picture and that would have been
fine. The simplest thing is this is your גט get if you
die in the middle of.
Retroactive גט. get.
A retroactive גט get if you die, if you die sometime today.
So if she lives, if she lives she's out of the picture.
If she dies she's out of the picture from the beginning of
the day. The only reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that is
because the גמרא Gemara already said you cannot give a גט get
on the condition that's connected to the woman's life. Right? That's the
duration of that's based on the woman's living or dying. You can't
give a גט get that way. So what we want to say
is this is your גט get if you die, okay, today, but
we can't say that. So we're going to say this is your
גט get if you go into a בית כנסת. beit knesset. We'll
make an arbitrary trigger. Now the point is, so we'll say it
looks like you're about to die you should go into a בית
כנסת, beit knesset, which is of course crazy. Right? So we're going
to change it a little bit but we're trying to have, we
want it to mean this is your גט get if you die,
okay, which would get you out of the picture and keep her
in, but that isn't a good condition so we have to substitute
a condition. Let's look at how the גמרא Gemara does it. Okay.
לשני אמר לה, Leshani amar lah,
to the second one you say, ולחדא אמר לה הרי זה גיטך
על מנת,
ulechada amar lah harei
zeh gittech al menat, excuse me, שלא תיכנסי לבית הכנסת. shelo tikanesi
leveit haknesset. You don't go into a שול. shul. Okay, so she's
dying presumably she's not going into a שול, shul, she'll die and
it won't work. So and then the גט get will kick in
and she'll be divorced. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, ודילמא לא
מתה חברתה, vedilma lo meitah chaverta,
maybe her friend does not die, ולא עיילא היא לבית
הכנסת. velo ayela hee leveit haknesset.
Meaning her friend, meaning number
one.
Number two doesn't die.
Right, number two doesn't die.
Right. Number two doesn't die and number one is living and is
happy and why should she go into a שול? shul? She doesn't
want to be divorced. דלא עיילא היא לבית הכנסת, Delo ayela hee
leveit haknesset, דהוו ליה לתרוייהו גיטא, dehavu leh letarvaihu gitta, and excuse
me, I said that wrong. Anyway, number two doesn't go, number one
doesn't go into שול shul and therefore it's a גט get because
the גט get is it takes effect if you don't go into
a שול. shul. וקאי בלא בית, Vekai belo bayit, and he doesn't
have. and and therefore he'll be not be married to any. So
if you try to say on the condition that if you don't
go into a בית כנסת, beit knesset, right? So the point should
be that she should be not going into a בית כנסת, beit
knesset, we only want this to be happening, don't go into a
בית כנסת, beit knesset, sort of in the condition that she's actually
going to die in the middle of the day. This is like
a substitute for the real condition we want to say, which is
if you die. So we say if you don't go into a
בית כנסת. beit knesset. But the גמרא Gemara is saying is, okay,
so if she actually dies and didn't go into a שול, shul,
it worked. But if she didn't die, right? How is she supposed
to know? Should I go into a שול, shul, should I not
go into a שול? shul? I'll go into a שול, shul, doesn't
look like I'm going to die. Then she dies. Okay, so I
don't go into a שול, shul, so she doesn't die. You can't
make this a substitute for the if you die condition. Okay, so
it winds up that that that she lives, okay, so he's out
of the picture. And if she lives, if she's living right now,
is she supposed to go into a שול shul or not go
into a שול? shul? How is she supposed to know if she's
going to die later today? Is essentially what the גמרא Gemara is
asking. If she chooses not to go into a שול shul because
she's afraid she might die or whatever who knows, and then she
dies, then he'll be having then neither of them will he be
married to. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא לחדא אמר לה,
ela lachada amar la, to one he says to her, הרי זה
גיטיך על מנת שלא תמות חברתך, harei ze gitich al mnat shelo
tamut chavertech,
like we said number two is your גט get if number one
doesn't die. ולחדא, ulchada, number one who we want to be divorced
in case she dies in the middle of the day, אמר לה,
amar la, he says to her, הרי זה גיטיך על מנת שאכנס
אני לבית הכנסת, harei ze gitich al mnat she'ekanes ani l'veit haknesset,
that I will go into a שול. shul. He's already in the
world's biggest שול, shul, but okay. דאי מיתה הקימא הא, de'i mita
hakaima ha, because
so if she die if number if number two dies, number one
is around. ואי מיתה הא קימא הא, ve'i mita ha kaima ha,
and if number one dies number two's around. מאי איכא למימר דילמא
מיתה חברתה בפלגא דיומא, mai ika l'meimar dilma mita chaverta b'palga d'yoma,
maybe number one will die in the middle of the day, ואתא
ליה איסורא למפרע דשתי בתים, ve'ata lehu avura l'mafrea b'shtei batim, and
he'll be married for the first part of the day with two
wives. דחזי לה דקבעי למימת, dechazi la dekabei l'meimat, if he sees
that she's about to die, קדים הוא ועייל לבית הכנסת, kadim hu
v'ayil l'veit haknesset, ומשוי ליה לגיטא דהא גיטא למפרע. umshavei lah l'gita
deha gita l'mafrea. So then he does it and makes it an
effective גט. get. Meaning what basically it's saying is this will be
your גט get if
if I the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, if I the כהן גדול
kohen gadol go into a שול. shul. Now that's a funny idea,
he's going to leave the בית המקדש beit hamikdash and go into
a שול, shul, but I don't know, let's say he says if
I the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, do X. Doesn't really matter what
X is. So basically here's the story, okay? If one lives and
is healthy, two is out of the picture, okay? If if one
dies at the beginning of the day, then two is in the
picture. The only point is if one dies in the middle of
the day, then for the first half there'll be overlap. How do
you get? So what he says is if it looks like my
first wife is about to die, then I will go ahead and
do whatever the condition is and that'll make her retroactively divorced from
me. I will trigger it, right?
So you know when יום כיפור Yom Kippur comes and one is
alive and well, two is not automatically divorced?
Well no, because one could be alive and well but die in
the middle of the day and then he wants to be married
to number to number two.
Wants to be married.
So if they're
trying to cover, let's do the four cases. Okay, if they both
die, wait, let's if they both die, well we're not concerned that
they're both going to die, that we said before. If they both
live, okay, then this one's out of the picture, number two is
out of the picture, right? Okay, if one lives and one dies,
well if two dies and one lives that's fine too, one is
in the picture. So the only question is if one dies and
two lives, which is what we're trying which is the whole purpose
for this, if one dies and two lives. If one dies and
two lives and it's middle of the day, then for the rest
of the day you've got number two, but for the first half
of the day you have the overlap. Right. So to cover that
overlap number one gets a גט get at the beginning of the
day and basically the כהן גדול kohen gadol says I will do
something to trigger that גט get when it looks like you're about
to die. Okay, and then he does that thing and then she's
retroactively divorced and then he has number one. Pretty complicated. The whole
thing could have been solved if either the גמרא Gemara didn't have
a problem of two wives, which the גמרא Gemara said which wasn't
obvious, or it didn't assume that it had to be נישואין. nisuin.
If it could have been קידושין, kiddushin, then you could have just
married number two on condition at the moment when number one drops
out of the picture. Yes. All right so let's just try to
get a little bit further.
Except that on שבת shabbos you don't give a גט.
get. Well that's too the גט get was ערב יום כיפור, erev
yom kippur, took effect retroactively.
I just want to say one sort of thing that's so interesting
here, it's lost because of because of the issue. Yeah. We're talking
about יום כיפור Yom Kippur through the עבודה avodah on יום הכיפורים
Yom HaKippurim and there are synagogues, the בית המקדש beit hamikdash is
a שול shul and we take for granted what are they doing
in all these synagogues? Right.
Well the גמרא Gemara might be a little anachronistic and
retro-projecting, but it
had no problem being that, in other words it's so.
I also like הכנסת לבית הכנסת Haknesset le-Beit ha-Knesset like I said,
he's in the world's biggest שול, shul, שהכנסת לבית הכנסת. she-Haknesset le-Beit
ha-Knesset. Anyway, fine. Okay, yes, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. מתקיף לה רב
אשי. Matkif lah Rav Ashi. Now we're thankfully done with that. So
רב אשי's Rav Ashi challenge. It said, ויתימא רב אבירא. ve-itema Rav
Avira. אלא מעתה, Ella me-ata, now that you say that the idea
of בית bayit means one wife and not two wives, and remember
I made that point, you know, the unique one כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, one wife. That idea that you're reading the word בית bayit
to mean only one wife, does that really work in other הלכות?
halachot? אלא מעתה, Ella me-ata, שתי יבמות הבאות מבית אחד לא יתייבמו.
shte yevamot ha-ba'ot mi-bayit echad lo yityabmu.
Because let's say a man dies and he has two wives, so
you should say you shouldn't and no children, you should say you're
not allowed to do ייבום yibbum because the פסוק pasuk by ייבום
yibbum says אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו. asher lo yivneh et
beit achiv.
בית. Bayit. So maybe ייבום yibbum is only when there's one house,
one wife, not two בית. bayit. We never say such a thing.
The whole מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot is all about a man dying
with multiple wives. Right? The first משנה. Mishna. So why don't you
say one בית bayit and not two בית? bayit? So the גמרא
Gemara
says יבמתו
יבמתו ריבה. Yevimto yevimto ribah. It says,
you know,
sister-in-law, sister-in-law, excuse me, twice to tell me that even if that
you know that even two wives are in the פרשה parsha of
ייבום. yibbum. מתקיף לה רבינא ויתימא רב שרביא. Matkif lah Ravina ve-itema
Rav Shravya. אלא מעתה, Ella me-ata, ארוסה לא תתייבם? arusah lo tityabbem?
Similar question. If בית bayit means one and בית bayit means נישואין,
nisu'in, not קידושין, kiddushin, so number one, ייבום yibbum should only be
with one wife. And we don't say that, so we had a
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, but it should only be with the woman that
the man was that there was already נישואין nisu'in with, not with
an ארוסה, arusah, because בית bayit means according to you only after
נישואין. nisu'in. So ארוסה לא תתייבם. Arusah lo tityabbem. So it says
החוצה, ha-chutzah, the wife shouldn't go outside to another man, somehow לרבות
את הארוסה. lerabot et ha-arusah. So this includes an ארוסה, arusah, so
which if you look at the side it mentions that רש"י Rashi
says החוצה ha-chutzah suggests a woman that's a little bit on the
outside, a woman that has yet to be brought into her husband's
house. So you're right, בית bayit should mean logically anyway you should
think about it, ייבום yibbum logically should be limited to a woman
that the man was that there was נישואין. nisu'in. Because ייבום yibbum
is about not having had children and there was a potential of
having children. Before
נישואין, nisu'in, before they're living together, the concept of, you know, sex
and children is not really on the table.
That's why your question of the ארוסה. arusah.
Well, yes, but so but the it's a good הוה אמינא. hava
amina. But the answer is החוצה ha-chutzah means even a woman that's
still somewhat at the outside still is in that פרשה. parsha. Okay,
so basically we've created this huge headache for ourselves saying that the
word בית bayit means נישואין, nisu'in, because it could have easily been
פשט pshat if it just meant קידושין, kiddushin, and also saying it
means one. So then the גמרא Gemara says logically then ייבום yibbum
should only be with one woman and only after נישואין. nisu'in. So
the גמרא Gemara has special פסוקים pesukim to say that technically yes,
but ייבום yibbum actually applies even if there are two wives and
ייבום yibbum actually applies even if the woman is an ארוסה arusah
and not a נשואה. nesu'ah. Okay, so let's take just get a
little bit further. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו
אוכל. Kohen Gadol makriv onen ve-eino ochel. So a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol can bring קרבנות korbanot if he's an אונן. onen. Vice versa
what the פסוק pasuk says ומן המקדש לא יצא, u-min ha-Mikdash lo
yetzei, that even when a father or mother dies he doesn't leave
the בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash. So he does his עבודה avodah when
he's an אונן onen after the immediate death of a relative, of
an immediate relative, but he can't eat the קרבנות korbanot when he's
an אונן. onen. It only allows him to do the עבודה, avodah,
not to eat the קרבנות. korbanot. רבי יהודה אומר כל היום כל
היום. Rabbi Yehuda omer kol ha-yom kol ha-yom. No, the whole day.
What does that mean? מאי כל היום? Mai kol ha-yom? What does
the whole day mean? So אמר רבא לא נצרכה אלא להביאו מתוך
ביתו. Amar Rava lo nitzrecha ella le-havi'o mi-toch beito. It means we
are so insistent that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol not only is
allowed to do the עבודה avodah as an אונן, onen, but demonstrates
that he does the עבודה avodah as an אונן, onen, that even
if he's at home when a relative dies, we schlep him out
of his house and we bring him to the בית המקדש Beit
ha-Mikdash to do the עבודה avodah as an אונן. onen. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה אביי. amar leh Abaye. Abaye said back
to him, הא לרבי יהודה אפוקי מפקינן ליה. Ha le-Rabbi Yehuda afokei
mafkinan leh. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we would actually take
a normal כהן Kohen away from the עבודה avodah when he's an
אונן. onen. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braitah, היה עומד
ומקריב על גבי המזבח. hayah omed u-makriv al gabei ha-mizbe'ach. Now a
normal כהן Kohen is only כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that can do
the עבודה avodah as an אונן. onen. A normal כהן Kohen who
does the עבודה avodah as an אונן onen invalidates the עבודה. avodah.
But what if he was in the middle of the עבודה avodah
when he when a relative died? When a father mother died? What
would be the הלכה? halacha? So that's the discussion. הרי שהיה מקריב
על גבי המזבח ושמע שמת לו מת. Harei she-hayah makriv al gabei
ha-mizbe'ach ve-shama she-met lo met. He heard that an immediate relative died.
מניח עבודתו ויוצא דברי רבי יהודה. Maniach avodato ve-yozei divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that's it, stop the עבודה avodah in
the middle, leave, you're an אונן, onen, you would invalidate the עבודה.
avodah.
זו עבודה של יום הכיפורים? Zu avodah shel Yom ha-Kippurim?
No, no, no, any עבודה. avodah. We're not yet.
That's why it says ואינו אוכל. ve-eino ochel. Yeah, yeah. Because ייבום
yibbum would not be relevant.
Yeah, right, right, right. It's not yet clear how this is tying
in. This is a generic discussion. Generic discussion.
Not יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doing the
rest.
רב יוסי אומר יגמור.
Reb
Yosi omer yigmor.
רב יוסי Reb Yosi says a normal כהן, Kohen, again not יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, a normal כהן Kohen hears that he became an
אבל, avel, an אונן, onen, he finishes the עבודה avodah he's in
the middle of. So what do we say? So if רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda by a normal כהן, Kohen, not a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, is so much feels like the invalidity of the אנינות, aninut,
the problem of the אנינות, aninut, that he would interrupt him in
the middle of the עבודה, avodah, how do you think רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda could be saying is that for a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol you שלעפ shlep him out of his house and you make
him do the עבודה avodah as an אונן? onen? Again, this is
not יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, during the normal year.
ואת אמרת יוצא ve'at amarta yotzei by a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
משמעינן ליה מתוך ביתו, mash'minan lei mitokh beito, we שלעפ shlep him
out of his house? אלא אמר רבא Ela amar Rava so says
רבא, Rava, מאי כל היום, mai kol hayom, what does רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda mean when he says the whole day by a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol who does the עבודה avodah as an אונן? onen?
לומר Lomar to tell you שאינו עובד כל היום, she'eino oved kol
hayom, that basically he disagrees, biblically speaking yes a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol does the עבודה avodah as an אונן, onen, that's what it
says ומן המקדש לא יצא, u'min hamikdash lo yeitzei,
but rabbinically I'm not going to let him do the עבודה avodah
the entire day. Why not? גזירה שמא יאכל, Gezeira shema yokhal, because
I'm afraid that if he's doing the עבודה avodah again not on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, יוי, yoi, that's what you do, you do
the עבודה avodah and you eat from the קרבנות. korbanot. But at
night I'll let him do the עבודה, avodah, why? Because the biblical
status of אנינות aninut is only the day of death. So therefore
at night if he does the עבודה, avodah, like you know there's
not much עבודה avodah left to be done but turning over the
fats or whatever, if he ends up eating the קרבנות, korbanot, it's
not a problem because biblically he's not an אונן onen at night
even if rabbinically he is. But during the day I won't. So
it's not clear at all what this has to do yet with
us, but what we're, I'll just hint to you and we'll talk
about this tomorrow, what we're going to talk about is the scenario
that we're worried about, that his wife dies. If his wife dies,
we've been spending all of our time concerned about what happens to
the backup wife, there's another problem that happens if his wife dies,
which is what? He's an אונן! onen! So what's the story, can
he finish doing the עבודה avodah on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as
an אונן? onen?
Okay, so we will, no גזירה, gezeira, right, well that's, so we'll
pick up with this tomorrow, but again to repeat what's relevant for
us is a כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot stops doing the עבודה avodah
as an אונן, onen, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol continues, that's what
the דרש drash says ומן המקדש לא יצא, u'min hamikdash lo yeitzei,
he continues
doing the עבודה avodah as an אונן, onen, but he can't eat
from the קרבנות korbanot as an אונן. onen. So what we're going
to discuss tomorrow is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol if his wife
dies, how does he continue doing the עבודה avodah as an אונן?
onen? Okay, and if biblically he's allowed, is there this concern that
רב יהודה Reb Yehuda said I don't want him to do the
עבודה, avodah, he might come to eat? That's what we will figure
out as we pick up tomorrow.